THOMAS MCCLINTOCK

Address

1308 E Spring Street University of Arizona Tucson, Arizona, USA (631) 418-5304 On the web

https://github.com/tmcclintock tmcclintock@email.arizona.edu

PERSONAL STATEMENT

I am a PhD candidate at the University of Arizona Physics Department working with Professor Eduardo Rozo. I work on galaxy cluster mass calibration and cosmology, and cosmic emulators for the halo mass function and halo bias. I am a member of the Dark Energy Survey as well as the LSST-Dark Energy Science Collaboration. I have an MSc from the University of Edinburgh in High Performance Computing and a BA from Amherst College.

PUBLICATIONS

- McClintock T., et al., 2017, Weak-lensing mass calibration of redMaPPer galaxy clusters in DES Y1 data, MNRAS, in prep.
- McClintock T., et al., 2017, Emulating the halo mass function, ApJ, in prep.
- McClintock T., Hannah E., Lim K., 2017, Bayesian analysis of frisbee flights, Eur. J. Phys., in prep.
- Chang C., et al., 2017, The Splashback Feature around DES Galaxy Clusters: Galaxy Density and Weak Lensing Profiles, arxiv:1710.06808, submitted
- Friedrich O., et al., 2017, Density split statistics: joint model of counts and lensing in cells, arxiv:1710.05162, submitted
- Gruen D., et al., 2017, Density split statistics: Cosmological constraints from counts and lensing in cells in DES Y1 and SDSS, arxiv:1710.05045, submitted
- Melchior P., Gruen D., McClintock T. et al., 2017, Weak-lensing mass calibration of redMaP-Per Clusters in Dark Energy Survey Science Verification Data, MNRAS, 469, 4899
- Simet M., McClintock T. et al., 2017, Weak lensing measurements of the mass-richness relation of SDSS redMaPPer clusters, MNRAS, 466, 3103
- Melia F., McClintock T., 2015, Supermassive black holes in the early universe, RSPSA, 471, 449
- Melia F., McClintock T., 2015, A test of cosmological models using high-z measurements of H(z), AJ, 150, 6

RECENT WORK

- DES Y1 Weak lensing mass calibration: Determining the mass-richness relation for optically selected galaxy clusters. Performed the mass modeling, developed new software to accurately estimate the covariance of the data, performed statistical analysis on the results using Bayesian statistics and MCMC.
- DES SV Weak lensing mass calibration: Performed the mass modeling and statistical inference of the results. Implemented new code to account for cluster miscentering.
- Bayesian analysis of frisbee flights: Constrained physical parameters the govern the physics of frisbee flight mechanics, both in simulations and from video data. Co-advised an undergraduate thesis.
- PHYS 105: Introduction to scientific computing: Designed and taught my own curriculum for the class that is still used today. Integrated Python and data visualization into the course.
- Core Cosmology Library developer: Developed and tested code for CCL, the primary software for analysis to be used by LSST-DESC.

- Supermassive black holes in the early Universe: Demonstrated that high redshift supermassive black holes can form via Eddington accretion in the $R_h = ct$ Universe, even though this is impossible in Λ CDM.
- A test of cosmological models using high-z measurements of H(z): Compared the ability of Λ CDM and the $R_h = ct$ Universe to accommodate the distance-redshift relation given by cosmic chronometer data via model selection techniques.

AWARDS & HONORS

Galileo Circle Scholarship

College of Science Graduate Student Award for Teaching Outstanding Graduate Student Colloquium Presentation in Spring 2015

EDUCATION

University of Arizona, Department of Physics Tucson, Arizona, USA Doctor of Philosophy, Physics Sept. 2012 - Present University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh Parallel Computing Centre Edinburgh, Scotland, UK Masters of Science, High Performance Computing Sept. 2011 - July 2012 Amherst College, Amherst College Bachelor of Arts cum laude, Physics and Astronomy Sept. 2007 - May 2011

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

University of Arizona Department of Physics Graduate Student

Tucson, AZ Sept. 2012 - Present

Amherst, MA

- Member of the DES collaboration. Contributed to the cluster calibration, cluster cosmology, trough analysis, MOF optimization, and combined probes covariance emulation projects. Advised by Eduardo Rozo. Primary collaborators are Peter Melchior, Daniel Gruen, and Erin Sheldon.
- Member of LSST-DESC. Presented work on cluster calibration and contributed to the Core Cosmology Library. Advised by Eduardo Rozo. Primary collaborators are Elisa Chisari and Antonio Villareal.
- Analyzed the physics of frisbee flights, both through simulations and video analysis. Used Bayesian statistics and MCMC to constrain physical models of flight parameters, and set limits on the resolution and frames-per-second needed to be able to set constraints from video. Co-advised with Kevin Lim the thesis of Elizabeth Hannah.
- Worked on alternative cosmological models, specifically the $R_h = ct$ Universe. Advised by Fulvio Melia.

University of Edinburgh Edinburgh Parallel Copmuting Centre Graduate Student

Edinburgh, Scotland, UK Sept. 2011 - Aug. 2012

• Developed a parallelized verson of a tax and benefits simulation program to determine optimal policies based on individuals' lifestyles.

Amherst College Physics Department

Amherst, MA

Senior Thesis and Research Intern

Sept. 2010 - Aug. 2011

• Calculated the positron production rate from low-mass x-ray binary star systems and compared it to 511 keV flux measurements in the galactic bulge.

Brookhaven National Laboratory

Brookhaven, NY

Research Intern

June 2010 - Aug. 2010; June 2009 - Aug. 2009

- SULI student scientist at the National Synchrotron Light Source under Dario Arena.
- Developed control systems for ferromagnetic resonance experiments.

• Designed and machined an electromagnet for the U4B beamline for use in x-ray magnetic circular dichroism experiments.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

University of Arizona Department of Physics

Tucson, AZ

- Co-advised an undergraduate thesis researching the physics of frisbee flights.
- Designed and taught a new curriculum for the PHYS 105:Introduction to Scientific Computing that is still used today.
- Teaching assistant for PHYS 182: Laboratory Electromagnetism and Optics.
- Teaching assistant for PHYS 105:Introduction to Scientific Computing and PHYS 305: Computational Physics.
- Grader for PHYS 321: Theoretical Mechanics.
- Tutored college and high school students in mechanics, electromagnitism, optics, and statistical mechanics.

Amherst College Department of Physics

Amherst, MA

- Grader for statistical mechanics, and introduction to electromagnitism.
- Resident councilor for three years. Worked two years in first-year dormitories and one year in upperclass housing. Assisted residents adjusting to college life and acted as a liaison between students, faculty, and staff.
- Tutored high school AP Physics students.

OUTREACH & LEADERSHIP

- Cosmology journal club organizer. Assemble the weekly reading list and assign readings.
- Secretary and Treasurer for the Women in Physics club. Served as judge for science fairs in local middle and high schools, attended outreach events in local schools and after-school clubs, and worked at the Physics booth at the Tucson Festival of Books.
- Astrobites guest author for a paper on the cosmic lithium problem in Big Bang nucleosynthesis (article link).
- College of Science representative to the Graduate and Professional Student Council. Primary achievement was procuring funds to restock department libraries.
- Elected to the Graduate Student Council in the physics department. Coordinated 'town hall' meetings between graduate students and department heads, arranged pizza lunches with colloquium speakers, organized weekly graduate student research presentations, and invited colloquium speakers voted on by graduate students.
- Speaker and co-organizer for the celebration of the 30th anniversary of the Nobel Prize in Medicine given to Barbara McClintock.